<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The excellency of the Protestant faith as to its objects and supports in a sermon preached November 5th, 1689 / by T. Cruso.</title>
            <author>Cruso, Timothy, 1656?-1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35320</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7438</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24865</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08626095</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08626095</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41492</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35320)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41492)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1254:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The excellency of the Protestant faith as to its objects and supports in a sermon preached November 5th, 1689 / by T. Cruso.</title>
                  <author>Cruso, Timothy, 1656?-1697.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 25 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.R. for John Salusbury,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Protestantism --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41492:1"/>
            <p>THE EXCELLENCY OF THE Proteſtant Faith, AS TO IT'S <hi>Objects and Supports.</hi> IN A SERMON Preached <hi>November</hi> 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, 1689. By <hi>T. CR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SO.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSALM 18.31.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>For who is God ſave the Lord? Or who is a Rock ſave our God?</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. R.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Salusbury,</hi> at the Riſing <hi>Sun,</hi> near the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:41492:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41492:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THough the Judaical <hi>Obſervation of Times</hi> (ſuch as their Anniverſary Feaſts of the <hi>Paſſeover, Pentecoſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Galat. 4.10.</note> and <hi>Tabernacles</hi> were) be forbidden to the Goſpel-Church, and no Day (excepting the <hi>firſt</hi> of the Week) hath now any ſtated Holineſs in it more than another, yet an <hi>oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſional Commemoration</hi> of Judgments and Mercies upon thoſe Dayes, which God himſelf hath ſignalized; may be an uſeful means to faſten a <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Impreſſion</hi> of both upon us, as well as to tranſmit the moſt <hi>Effectual Notice</hi> of God's won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Works to following Ages. As it is not fit that we ſhould ceaſe <hi>to humble our ſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Hand of God,</hi> ſo ſoon as any Calamity is removed, ſo on the other ſide, we ſhould not leave off to <hi>rejoyce in his Goodneſs,</hi> immediately af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:41492:3"/>it hath paſs't before us. That which is done in one Generation,<note place="margin">Pſal. 102.18.</note> muſt be <hi>written for the Generation to come, and the People which ſhall be created, ſhall praiſe the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is too evident, by the <hi>Infidelity</hi> which hath reign'd among us, that we in this Nation had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten the <hi>God of our Fathers,</hi> and worn out the ſenſe of former Deliverances; God's reſcuing of them heretofore out of a danger which they <hi>ſaw not,</hi> was little thought of for our own Encouragement, in the midſt of Dangers which we <hi>did ſee;</hi> the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy was almoſt <hi>buried</hi> in the <hi>Graves</hi> of thoſe who primarily receiv'd it; and though we ſtill ſhar'd in its happy Conſequences, yet it ſcarcely infus'd any more <hi>Life</hi> into our Faith, than if the remembrance of it had heen quite <hi>extinct.</hi> We <hi>look'd forward</hi> ſo much upon the Miſeries which we had in proſpect, that there were few,<note place="margin">Pſal. 77.5.</note> who <hi>look't back upon the days of old,</hi> or that <hi>conſider'd the years of Ancient times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding this, and other ſad Tokens which were upon us, of our great Unmindfulneſs of God, (who had been a <hi>Known</hi> and a <hi>Tryed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge</hi>) he was pleaſed very ſeaſonably now again to <hi>make bare his Arm</hi> in our own time, and to <hi>put a new Song into our Mouths,</hi> which contains in it more matter of thankful Admiration, than the former did; ſo that we ſeem to have the Portion of
<pb facs="tcp:41492:3"/>
               <hi>Jacob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 49.26.</note> for <hi>our Bleſſings have prevailed above the Bleſſings of our Progenitors,</hi> and though our ſhameful degeneracy forbids us to think, that we are <hi>better than our Fathers</hi> (when indeed we are ſo notoriouſly <hi>worſe</hi>) yet we muſt ſay, that God hath appear'd more eminently for us, than he did for them. That which we have <hi>ſeen,</hi> exceeds what we have <hi>heard,</hi> and even in this caſe, the <hi>Younger</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance will claim a preheminence above the <hi>Elder.</hi> I ſpeak not this, as if one muſt therefore <hi>ſupplant,</hi> or blot out the memory of the other, for they both agree, and conſiſt very well together; and the <hi>ſame</hi> day having <hi>two</hi> ſuch remarkable <hi>Seals</hi> fixt upon it by Providence, it will ſurely be very Famous to all our Poſterities, as long as the <hi>Proteſtant Name</hi> endures in <hi>England,</hi> which I hope will be, as long as the World it ſelf remains. I doubt not, but that they who ſincerely value <hi>either</hi> of theſe, will triumph in them <hi>both;</hi> and therefore if there be any who ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly repine at this <hi>laſt,</hi> 'tis no uncharitable imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to ſuppoſe, that they are really diſpleas'd with the <hi>firſt</hi> alſo; for the <hi>diſtance</hi> of <hi>Fourſcore and Three Years</hi> between them is not ſo conſiderable as the <hi>Affinity</hi> of their <hi>Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt add to obviate the Exceptions of <hi>Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> or <hi>Enemies,</hi> that this Diſcourſe had never been made more publick, than it was firſt made by Preaching, if the Authors intentions could have ſtood
<pb facs="tcp:41492:4"/>againſt the deſires of the Hearers; and therefore the expoſing of it thus to common view, which was never framed with any ſuch deſign, muſt be laid at their door, and not at mine. If it might but fall into the hands of as favourable Readers, and be attended with a Bleſſing from Heaven in the peruſal, I ſhould however chearfully expect, that its numerous Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections would in Charity be overlookt, and the main Truths entertain'd with ſome good ſucceſs; they that neglect the <hi>Treaſure</hi> which is in <hi>Earthen Veſſels,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.7.</note> and only look with a cenſorious Eye to the <hi>droſſy part,</hi> are really moſt injurious to themſelves, and will loſe the benefit of far better and more valuable Performances, than this, or any of mine can be.</p>
            <p>I conclude with a ſpecial Requeſt to thoſe, who ſo earneſtly intreated this from me, that they would follow it with their Prayers to God, that it may <hi>go forth in his Name,</hi> and cloathed with a Divine Power, ſo as not to <hi>return void or empty to him that ſends it;</hi> and that my whole Service in the Miniſtry committed to me may be proſperous to thoſe that place themſelves under it, which will he the <hi>Glory and Joy</hi> of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The leaſt of God's Saints, and Unworthieſt of his Meſſengers, <hi>T. C.</hi>
               </signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>Novemb. 9. 1689</hi>
               </date>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41492:4"/>
            <head>THE EXCELLENCY OF THE <hi>PROTESTANT FAITH,</hi> AS TO IT'S <hi>Objects and Supports.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>DEUTERON. xxxii. 31.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For their Rock is not as our Rock, even our Enemies themſelves being Judges.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THIS Dying Song of <hi>Moſes</hi> (whereof the Words now mentioned are a part) is not only <hi>Hiſtorical,</hi> but <hi>Prophetical,</hi> contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome hints both of God's <hi>paſt</hi> and <hi>future</hi> Diſpenſations towards the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> His main ſcope and deſign in all, is to ſhew, that God was not to be blamed for his dealing with <hi>them,</hi> but they were to be condemned for revolting from <hi>him:</hi> And therefore
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41492:5"/>whatſoever Bleſſings they <hi>loſt,</hi> or Severities they <hi>felt,</hi> they muſt look upon their <hi>own Sin</hi> as the Cauſe and Reaſon of it. To this purpoſe, <hi>Moſes</hi> ſtarts the Queſtion in the words going before the Text,<note place="margin">Ver. 30.</note> 
               <hi>How ſhould One chaſe a Thouſand, and Two put Ten Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand to flight, except their Rock had ſold them, and the Lord had ſhut them up?</hi> This ſeems to be a ſtrange and ſurpriſing Contradiction to what God had promiſed by the ſame <hi>Moſes</hi> before;<note place="margin">Levit. 26.8.</note> 
               <hi>Five of you ſhall chaſe an Hundred, and an Hundred of you ſhall put Ten Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand to flight;</hi> (which was repeated, as to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of it,<note place="margin">Joſh. 23.10.</note> by his Succeſſor <hi>Joſhua,</hi> when he called the People together, towards the cloſe of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.) They might therefore now wonder to hear, that One of <hi>their Adverſaries</hi> ſhould chaſe a Thouſand of Them; though indeed the threatning grew more familiar to them afterwards; for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet tells them, <hi>One Thouſand ſhall flee at the rebuke of One;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 30.17.</note> 
               <hi>at the rebuke of Five ſhall you ſtee, till you are left as a Beacon upon the top of a Mountain,</hi> &amp;c. But this Riddle is eaſily reſolved; the Promiſe before ſpoken of, was upon the ſuppoſition of their Obedience; and conſequently when they <hi>ſold them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by their Iniquities</hi> (which is laid to their charge,<note place="margin">chap. 50.1.</note>) it might well be expected that <hi>their Rock ſhould ſell them</hi> in a way of Judgment, and when they <hi>withheld</hi> (or impriſon'd,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.18.</note> like the <hi>Heathen</hi>) <hi>the Truth in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs,</hi> they might rationally think, that the <hi>Lord would ſhut them up</hi> in a ſtate of Miſery and Thraldom.</p>
            <p>Now leſt they or their Adverſaries ſhould over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>look the <hi>Divine Hand</hi> in ſo marvellous a change, and more eſpecially leſt their <hi>Adverſaries</hi> ſhould (who were apt to ſay, as we read in this very Chapter, <hi>Our hand is high,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 27.</note> 
               <hi>and the Lord hath not done all this</hi>)
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41492:5"/>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> adds in theſe words, <hi>For their Rock is not,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>q. d.</hi> Tho Multitudes of the Heathens ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated by a few of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> it would be no ſtrange thing, becauſe their Idol-Gods can do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all for their <hi>protection,</hi> and on the other ſide, if many of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> be vanquiſht by a ſmall number of the Heathen, which carryes a more aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing appearance, it cannot be, becauſe thoſe Idols act for their <hi>aſſiſtance,</hi> but becauſe our God does <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw</hi> that help from us, which he is able to <hi>afford</hi> to us.</p>
            <p>We have here in the Text it ſelf <hi>two</hi> particulars conſiderable. 1. The <hi>Preference</hi> of the true God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all others. <hi>[Their Rock is not as our Rock.]</hi> The <hi>Rock</hi> is a Title given to God not only in this, and the preceding Verſe, but thrice before in this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and very often in the Book of <hi>Pſalms.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 4.15, 18.</note> Rocks anciently being places of ſhelter which Men uſed to fly unto in times of danger and diſtreſs;<note place="margin">1 Sam. 13.6.</note> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Holy <hi>David</hi> calls God the <hi>Rock of his Refuge.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 94.22.</note>2. The <hi>Acknowledgment</hi> of this by <hi>Iſraels</hi> Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. <hi>[Even our Enemies themſelves being Judges.]</hi> They that were ſo ready to <hi>reproach</hi> and <hi>blaſpheme the Name of God,</hi> as well as to <hi>boaſt</hi> and <hi>magnifie themſelves,</hi> yet could not deny this. It was owned not only by their <hi>Friends</hi> and Favourers,<note place="margin">Exod. 18.11. Joſh. 2.11. Exod. 14.18. 1 Sam. 4.8.</note> ſuch as <hi>Jethro</hi> was, and <hi>Rahab,</hi> but alſo by their worſt and greateſt <hi>Oppoſers,</hi> ſuch as the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and <hi>Philiſtins</hi> too. So that <hi>Moſes</hi> his <hi>Appeal</hi> to the Heathens here, is much like that which God made to the <hi>Inhabitants of Jeruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 5.3.</note> 
               <hi>and the Men of Judah</hi> in their own caſe,<note place="margin">Acts 4.19.</note> or like that which the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> made to the <hi>Jewiſh Rulers, whether it be right in the ſight of God, to hearken unto you more than unto God, judge ye.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:41492:6"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">v. </seg>37</label> 
               <hi>Two</hi> things are evidently <hi>preſuppoſed.</hi> 1. That <hi>There are no Perſons in the World, but what have ſome ROCK or other to be the object of their Confidence.</hi> When <hi>Iſrael</hi> caſt off the <hi>God of Abraham, the Fear of Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>the Portion of Jacob,</hi> they choſe <hi>new Gods;</hi> they did not turn perfect <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> but they had <hi>their</hi> Gods ſtill (though poor counterfeit ones) as <hi>the Rock in whom they truſted.</hi> So the other <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Nations</hi> had their ſeveral <hi>Deities</hi> whom they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended on for all neceſſary ſuccours, as well as paid a reſpect and veneration to. This is included in what the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſays,<note place="margin">Micah 4.5.</note> 
               <hi>All People will walk, every one in the Name of his God.</hi> Every Man is naturally ſenſible, that he is not a <hi>ſelf-ſufficient</hi> being, and therefore ſeeks after ſomething <hi>without</hi> himſelf, to believe in. Men chuſe rather to exerciſe Faith upon that which indeed <hi>is not God</hi> (as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaks in this ſame <hi>Song</hi>) becauſe it hath the <hi>Name,</hi>
               <note place="margin">v. 21.</note> than to live abſolutely without <hi>any</hi> God at all. 2. <hi>The Church and the World do not repoſe their truſt in the ſame God.</hi> Their Rock, and our Rock are different. The People of God, and the reſt of Mankind, agree no better in their <hi>confidences,</hi> than they do in their <hi>delights,</hi> and many other things; as they do not <hi>love</hi> the ſame Objects, ſo they do not <hi>lean upon</hi> the ſame. <hi>Some truſt</hi> (ſays the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi>) <hi>in Chariots,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 20.7.</note> 
               <hi>and ſome in Horſes, but we will remember the Name of the Lord our God.</hi> Many that pretend to believe and reſt upon our Rock, will be ſure firſt to <hi>hew</hi> him after their own fancies; they <hi>ſhape</hi> and <hi>faſhion</hi> a God according as may pleaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; but then it muſt be conſider'd, that if Men do not take him as the <hi>Scripture</hi> repreſents him, he is not the <hi>ſame,</hi> but <hi>another</hi> God. Many pretend a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyance upon him, but they make <hi>other things</hi> their ſupports in <hi>conjunction with him,</hi> which is really the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41492:6"/>
               <hi>having of more Gods than one;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 52.2, 6.</note> whereas we ſhould ſay with <hi>David, He only is my Rock, and my Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>principal</hi> thing to be <hi>Obſerved</hi> from the Words, is,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Doct.</note> That <hi>the true Church of God is intitled to the beſt Rock, in the Judgment of her very Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the proſecuting of this, I ſhall endeavour to ſhew,
<list>
                  <item>I. In what reſpects God may be ſtyled the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Rock.</item>
                  <item>II. How it appears, that this Rock is better than that of her Enemies.</item>
                  <item>III. Whence it comes to paſs, that 'tis better even in their Judgment, who yet reject and oppoſe it.</item>
                  <item>IV. Conclude with ſome Inferences, by way of Application, <hi>eſpecially to this day.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> 
               <hi>Firſt</hi> of all, I am to ſhew upon what accounts God may be ſtyled the Churches Rock, This ſhoul'd be open'd diſtinctly under theſe <hi>two</hi> Heads, why is he called a <hi>Rock</hi> in general, and why <hi>our</hi> Rock in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I ſhall enquire, why God hath this <hi>general Name</hi> and Character of a <hi>Rock</hi> given to him here. Not to run into the imprudent <hi>extream</hi> of alledging thoſe reſemblances which are <hi>forc't,</hi> or <hi>foreign</hi> to this matter, I ſhall only inſiſt upon <hi>three,</hi> which the Spirit of God himſelf does expreſly propound to us. The In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite God may be very fitly ſet forth by a Rock, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of <hi>Height, Fixedneſs,</hi> and <hi>Strength.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, God is juſtly term'd a <hi>Rock</hi> in reſpect of <hi>Height.</hi> Rocks are uſually of an <hi>Elevated Situation</hi> above the other adjacent parts. As this is commonly known, and need not be laboriouſly prov'd, ſo the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41492:7"/>Holy Ghoſt does particularly refer to it in this caſe. The promiſe to him,<note place="margin">Iſa. 33.16.</note> that <hi>walketh Righteouſly, and ſpeaketh uprightly</hi> (as diſtinguiſht from the <hi>Sinners in</hi> Zion) is, that <hi>he ſhall dwell on high, his place of defence ſhall be the Munition of Rocks.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 61.2.</note> Accordingly, <hi>David</hi> in the midſt of his Troubles, when his <hi>Heart was overwhelmed,</hi> cryes out to God, <hi>Lead me to the Rock which is higher than I.</hi> And elſewhere ſpeaking of the <hi>Jews</hi> in the time of their Affliction,<note place="margin">Pſal. 78.35.</note> he ſays, that <hi>they remembred that God was their Rock, and the high God their Redeemer.</hi> God is often deſcrib'd, as the <hi>Lofty one,</hi> and one that's <hi>higher than the higheſt.</hi> And the <hi>Moſt High God</hi> is the Name whereby he is called no leſs than four times within the compaſs of five Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.<note place="margin">Gen. 14.18, 19, 20, 22.</note> This may not only be underſtood of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſibleneſs</hi> of God's Nature, (who is <hi>far above our ſight,</hi> and out of the <hi>reach</hi> of our thoughts) but alſo, and as I conceive, principally of his <hi>Sovereignty</hi> and <hi>Dominion;</hi> for all Creatures as they are vaſtly <hi>inferiour,</hi> ſo they are perfectly <hi>ſubject</hi> to him. This is a great ſecurity to the Church, that their God hath every thing <hi>at his foot,</hi> and under his abſolute Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; his proceedings are unaccountable, and his purpoſes uncontroulable; for he is the <hi>Supreme,</hi> and therefore (as the Prophet ſpeaks) we may <hi>rejoyce in his Highneſs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 13.3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, God may be ſtyled a <hi>Rock,</hi> in reſpect of <hi>Fixedneſs.</hi> Rocks are counted ſome of the moſt ſtable parts of this lower Creation; and therefore when the Holy Ghoſt would repreſent a <hi>more than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary ſtorm</hi> of Divine diſpleaſure, he ſays, that <hi>the Rocks are thrown down by him;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nah. 1.6.</note> which implyes, that they are not lyable to <hi>common ſhakings.</hi> Our Saviour tells us of the <hi>Wiſe Man who built his Houſe upon a Rock,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 7.24, 25.</note> 
               <hi>and the rain deſcended, and the floods came, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41492:7"/>the Winds blew and beat upon that Houſe, but it fell not, for it was founded upon a Rock.</hi> This ſhadows out to us the <hi>firm unſhaken</hi> Counſels of the <hi>Immutable</hi> God, who from Everlaſting, and to Everlaſting, is free from the leaſt Alteration either in his <hi>Being,</hi> or <hi>Will.</hi> He does not <hi>turn,</hi> and <hi>waver</hi> to and fro, as the beſt and nobleſt of his Creatures (witneſs the fall of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> and <hi>Men</hi>) are prone of themſelves to do, but is alwayes in <hi>one State,</hi> and of <hi>one mind.</hi> This is a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty advantage to us alſo; as himſelf ſays,<note place="margin">Mal. 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>I am the Lord, I change not, therefore ye Sons of Jacob are not conſumed.</hi> An unchangeable God is the Author of the Churches <hi>ſtability,</hi> or elſe ſhe had been long ago <hi>toſs't</hi> by the <hi>hand of Violence,</hi> and <hi>kickt</hi> by the <hi>foot of Pride</hi> out of the World;<note place="margin">Pſa. 46.5.</note> but <hi>God is in the midst of her,</hi> and (for that reaſon) <hi>ſhe ſhall not be moved.</hi> His <hi>Eye and Heart</hi> which at the firſt were chiefly plac'd upon his People, can never be <hi>taken off</hi> from them; there is no more variableneſs in his <hi>Affection,</hi> than un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty in his <hi>duration;</hi> he may as ſoon be <hi>pluckt out of his Throne,</hi> as the <hi>graving of Zion be raced out of the Palms of his Hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, God may be truly ſet forth under the notion of a <hi>Rock,</hi> upon the account of <hi>ſtrength.</hi> When <hi>Balaam</hi> look't upon the <hi>Kenites,</hi> (a People very well fortifyed) he took up this <hi>Parable,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 24.21.</note> 
               <hi>Strong is thy dwelling place, and thou putteſt thy reſt in a Rock.</hi> We know, that one of the <hi>Miracles</hi> at our Saviours Paſſion, was <hi>the rending of the Rocks.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 27.51.</note> What Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments have force enough to enter into them? They that <hi>ſplit</hi> and break ſo many other things, ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main <hi>whole</hi> and entire themſelves. This plainly holds forth to us the <hi>Eternal Power of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 17.10.</note> who is called the <hi>Rock of our ſtrength.</hi> Omnipotence is <hi>eſſential</hi> to him,<note place="margin">Pſal. 21.13.</note> and therefore <hi>David</hi> mentions his being <hi>exalted in his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41492:8"/>own ſtrength,</hi> to difference him from us, and ſuch as we are, becauſe all created ſtrength is <hi>borrowed,</hi> and ſeparable from the Creature. How ſecurely there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can God bid defiance to the poor <hi>feeble</hi> attempts of Devils and Men, who receive that ſtrength <hi>from</hi> him, which they exert <hi>againſt</hi> him! How apparently unavoidable is it, that whoſoever <hi>daſhes</hi> againſt this <hi>Rock,</hi> muſt be <hi>broken!</hi> As this ſhould put God's Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies in <hi>fear,</hi> (who contend with one that is infinitely <hi>mightier</hi> than themſelves) ſo 'tis a very encouraging Motive of his Peoples <hi>Truſt;</hi> the <hi>Weakneſs of God</hi> may much better be relyed on, than <hi>Humane Power,</hi> when it is at its <hi>utmoſt pitch.</hi> What is an <hi>Arm of Fleſh</hi> to the <hi>Arm of the Lord?</hi> How <hi>Invincible</hi> is he, and they that confide in him? Nothing can make any <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition,</hi> if he think fit to <hi>prevent</hi> it, nothing can have any <hi>ſucceſs,</hi> if he reſolve to <hi>blaſt</hi> it. He is able to <hi>do</hi> all that he <hi>deſires,</hi> and to <hi>undo</hi> all that is <hi>endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd</hi> by any of his Adverſaries.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I am to examine, why God is called <hi>our</hi> Rock; how comes the <hi>Church</hi> to have this <hi>peculiar propriety</hi> in him, as divided from the <hi>World.</hi> There is a twofold <hi>Right,</hi> or foundation for this claim; <hi>God's Covenant,</hi> and <hi>our Choice;</hi> becauſe he hath freely <hi>gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> himſelf to us, and we (if we are <hi>born from above</hi>) have unfeignedly <hi>received</hi> him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, God is <hi>our</hi> Rock by <hi>Covenant:</hi> As he hath engaged, and <hi>betrothed</hi> himſelf to us, and us to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>for ever,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 2.19.</note> 
               <hi>in Righteouſneſs, and in Judgment, in Loving kindneſs, and in Mercies.</hi> None can doubt, (unleſs they aſſume more boldneſs to <hi>clip</hi> the <hi>Divine Prerogative,</hi> than that of <hi>Man</hi>) but that God <hi>may</hi> communicate a <hi>diſtinct and ſeparate Intereſt</hi> in himſelf to whomſoever he pleaſeth; and every one who knows the Scripture, muſt know that God <hi>does not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41492:8"/>pleaſe</hi> to communicate any ſuch Intereſt, but to his Church <hi>only,</hi> as a Society call'd out of the World. The reſt of Mankind, as they have a rooted Principle of <hi>Atheiſm</hi> in their <hi>Hearts,</hi> and ſay that <hi>there is no God,</hi> ſo they have indeed <hi>as little relation</hi> to him, <hi>as if there were none.</hi> There is no <hi>General Covenant</hi> made ſince the fall with <hi>all</hi> the Children of <hi>Adam,</hi> but a <hi>ſpecial Covenant of Grace</hi> with all the <hi>faithful,</hi> which conveys a <hi>new</hi> Title to them, inſtead of the <hi>Old</hi> one, loſt by the firſt Apoſtacy. He that was <hi>a God to Abraham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 17.7.</note> and to his <hi>Natural Seed,</hi> excluding all other <hi>Nations,</hi> under the Old Teſtament, is a God to his <hi>Spiritual believing Seed,</hi> excluding all other <hi>Perſons</hi> whatſoever, now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the New Teſtament. God is not the <hi>ſame</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Men, as he is to his particular People; though he be cloath'd with the ſame <hi>Attributes,</hi> yet he does not <hi>exerciſe</hi> them <hi>alike.</hi> As for the <hi>Men of the Earth,</hi> he is not bound by <hi>promiſe to be their Rock,</hi> but on the contrary he is oblig'd by his <hi>threatnings</hi> to be <hi>their Revenger;</hi> his <hi>Truth</hi> does not tye him to <hi>defond,</hi> but to <hi>deſtroy</hi> them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, God is <hi>Our</hi> Rock by <hi>Choice,</hi> and volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary acceptance. All that are <hi>Iſraelites indeed</hi> have ſincerely taken the Lord to be <hi>their</hi> God, and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully rejoyce in him <hi>as ſuch.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jerem. 3.22.</note> 
               <hi>Behold we come unto thee,</hi> (ſays the Church) <hi>for thou art the Lord our God.</hi> Again, in another place, we find them making the like profeſſion:<note place="margin">Hoſ. 14.3.</note> 
               <hi>We will not ſay any more to the work of our hands, ye are our Gods.</hi> This <hi>Negative</hi> here implyes an <hi>Affirmative;</hi> their <hi>renouncing</hi> and aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning of <hi>falſe</hi> Gods did include their <hi>embracing</hi> of the <hi>true.</hi> Such Texts are ſo numerous, that 'tis need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs to cite them. The taking of God to be our Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler and our Portion, <hi>our Soveraign</hi> and <hi>our Shield</hi> is the very <hi>firſt</hi> thing, which truly <hi>adds us to the Church,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:41492:9"/>and manifeſts our ſaving Converſion. Till we place our happineſs and our ſecurity in him, and are willing to live both under God's <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>Protection,</hi> we are properly <hi>of the World,</hi> and <hi>walk according to its courſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 33.22.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord is our King, he will ſave us,</hi> is (as it were) the Natural and Primitive Language of all <hi>Returning Sinners,</hi> when they are effectually <hi>called to be Saints.</hi> God's <hi>offering</hi> of himſelf to us in the Unli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited Miniſtry of the Word, does not make him <hi>Ours</hi> (for he is offered to multitudes now, whom he will not <hi>know</hi> at laſt) but our hearty <hi>Complyance</hi> with it; 'tis a <hi>mutual agreement</hi> on both hands, which muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the <hi>Intereſt,</hi> and complete the <hi>Title.</hi> God is not to be lookt upon as <hi>our Rock,</hi> before the Spirit per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades and prevails with us to <hi>chuſe</hi> him; and if we are not perſwaded ſo to do, we are <hi>not really his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> though we may be <hi>called by his Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> The <hi>Second</hi> thing, is to ſhew, how it does appear, that our Rock, or the Rock which the Church is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled to, is <hi>better than that of our Enemies.</hi> If we <hi>compare</hi> them a little together, we ſhall quickly and eaſily ſee a vaſt <hi>Diſproportion.</hi> I only premiſe, that as a long <hi>continued Ridge</hi> of Hills is ſometimes reckoned by Geographers and others, as <hi>One</hi> Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, ſo <hi>their Rock</hi> (who are and have been the Churches greateſt Enemies) though it go under that <hi>ſingle denomination,</hi> is indeed a <hi>Conjunction of many things,</hi> which they make their Refuge, and eſteem their ſafety. I ſhall inſtance in ſix particulars, which may be comprehended under this General term.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, An <hi>Humane Head</hi> is <hi>their Rock.</hi> The dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate <hi>Roman Church</hi> does expreſly and openly avow this; they declare themſelves to be <hi>Originally</hi> headed by <hi>Peter,</hi> as the <hi>chief of the Apoſtles,</hi> and <hi>their Biſhop,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:41492:9"/>and <hi>Founder,</hi> and <hi>now</hi> by the <hi>Pope,</hi> as his <hi>Succeſſor.</hi> Let us look a little into both.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, As to <hi>Peter,</hi> though we ſhould grant him to be <hi>Biſhop of Rome</hi> (which is more than we need to do, becauſe no ſatisfying proof can be brought that ever <hi>he was there,</hi>) yet that he had the <hi>primacy</hi> among the reſt of his <hi>Brethren,</hi> the Apoſtles, and that the <hi>Chriſtian Church</hi> was <hi>founded</hi> upon him, is by no means to be allowed. The <hi>Text</hi> which they have urg'd to countenance this Opinion, hath been ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently and fully cleared, that I think they can ſcarcely <hi>abuſe</hi> it to do them any further ſervice.<note place="margin">Matth. 16.18.</note> 
               <hi>Thou art Peter, and on this Rock will I build my Church.</hi> The caſe in ſhort was this;<note place="margin">v. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> a little before had made a <hi>good confeſſion, Thou art Chriſt, the Son of the Living God; Chriſt</hi> requites him by ſaying alſo to him, <hi>Thou art Peter; q. d.</hi> Thou art fitly called ſo, (<hi>Peter</hi> ſignifying a Rock, or <hi>Stone:</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 1.42.</note>) And haſt made good this Character by the <hi>ſtedfaſtneſs</hi> of thy Faith in me; then he adds, (not upon <hi>thee</hi> Peter, but) <hi>upon this Rock will I build my Church; i. e.</hi> upon this <hi>Truth</hi> which thou haſt confeſs't, or upon <hi>my ſelf,</hi> who am the matter and ſubſtance of it. Certainly, if <hi>Peter</hi> were to have had ſo great a <hi>preheminence</hi> beyond his Fellows, our Lord would not have plac't them <hi>all</hi> equally upon <hi>twelve Thrones,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 19.28.</note> which utterly ſhuts out the pretence of exalting <hi>Peters Chair</hi> above the reſt. Beſides this, it deſerves to be remark't, that <hi>none</hi> of the Apoſtles (excepting the <hi>Son of Perdition,</hi> whoſe Charge was <hi>taken by another</hi>) <hi>fell ſo foulely,</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> did; none <hi>deny'd</hi> and <hi>abjur'd</hi> their Maſter, but only he; as if God had reſolv'd to <hi>diſcourage</hi> the deſign of advancing him to any ſuch <hi>Headſhip</hi> over the Church, as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> would put upon him. He that <hi>ſeem'd
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41492:10"/>to be a Pillar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Galat. 2.9.</note> was but left a while to himſelf, and he ſeem'd like <hi>a reed ſhaken with the wind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, As to the <hi>Pope,</hi> the preſent viſible <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> his <hi>Succeſſion</hi> to <hi>Peter</hi> in that Seat can never be clearly made out, and if it could, their caſe would not be much the better. We know very well, what abominable <hi>Monſters</hi> have poſſeſt both the place and the power, as even <hi>their own Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorians</hi> have reported; as <hi>Rome</hi> is <hi>ſpiritually called Sodom and Egypt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel. 11.8.</note> ſo that Chair hath been <hi>literally</hi> fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with <hi>unclean Sodomites,</hi> and <hi>Egyptian Sorcerers;</hi> as their <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> Church is often deſcribed by the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> ſo the Heads of it have been more properly <hi>Brutes</hi> than <hi>Men;</hi> and while they have lifted up themſelves <hi>above all that is called God,</hi> they have car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the notorious <hi>mark and Image of the Devil.</hi> The greateſt <hi>Deceivers</hi> that ever appeared in the World, have been their Men of <hi>Infullibility,</hi> and ſuch as have <hi>departed furtheſt</hi> from the Truth, have been their <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nerring</hi> Guides. If this Rock of <hi>theirs,</hi> be as <hi>our</hi> Rock, let all that have the leaſt part of an <hi>Eye to ſee,</hi> determine;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.4.</note> our Rock is <hi>Chriſt,</hi> (as the Rock of the <hi>Jewiſh Believers</hi> was) a Rock which no <hi>Darts</hi> of Temptation could <hi>pierce,</hi> and a Rock which <hi>ſtands faſt for ever;</hi> the <hi>Holy one of God,</hi> and the <hi>King Eternal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwritten Traditions</hi> are <hi>their Rock,</hi> and the <hi>Word of God</hi> is <hi>ours.</hi> What <hi>compariſon</hi> is there between theſe two? How many things have our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies deliver'd to the World as <hi>Oracles,</hi> which have been groſly falſe and <hi>fabulous!</hi> And how doubtful and uncertain muſt the beſt be, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how lyable they were to be alter'd and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prav'd, either through the <hi>remiſneſs</hi> or <hi>treachery</hi> of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41492:10"/>thoſe into whoſe hands they came! How hardly can we credit a <hi>report</hi> in our own times, after it hath been propagated from one to another, unleſs we trace it to the <hi>Spring!</hi> How many times are we deluded and miſtaken in things which are but <hi>of Yeſterday!</hi> How much more when Traditions are pretended of ſo great <hi>Antiquity!</hi> But indeed, 'tis a great temptation to Men to <hi>leave the Word of God,</hi> and ſeek out other ſupports, when they find that the Word is <hi>againſt</hi> them; if the Bible could be <hi>ſuborn'd</hi> as a poſitive Witneſs in their Cauſe, they would not fly to theſe <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſcriptural Sanctuaries;</hi> they are forc't (as it were) to <hi>ſay ſomething of this kind,</hi> that they may not be <hi>ſpeechleſs.</hi> How much ſafer and happier are we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, who are <hi>built upon the foundation of the Apoſtles and Prophets!</hi> We are able to ſay with <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.20.</note> that we <hi>hope in the Word;</hi> and we believe as the <hi>Sacred Canon</hi> directs us to believe, but no otherwiſe. Our <hi>Faith</hi> does not lean upon the <hi>Words of Men,</hi> but the <hi>Inſpired Writings</hi> of thoſe that <hi>came from God;</hi> which the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> commends as <hi>more ſure than a voice from Heaven.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.18, 19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Images, Reliques,</hi> and the <hi>Conſecrated Elements</hi> are <hi>their Rock.</hi> (I joyn all theſe together, as having ſome <hi>affinity</hi> one to another, and being of equal <hi>ſignification, i.e.</hi> of none at all.) What confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence do the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> place in <hi>Images,</hi> as if thoſe lifeleſs repreſentations <hi>(like the ſhadow of Peter paſſing by)</hi> could perform extraordinary matters!<note place="margin">Acts 5.15.</note> A piece of folly and ſtupidity, which cannot be better de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd, than in the words of the Pſalmiſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 115.8.</note> 
               <hi>They that make them, are like unto them, and ſo is every one that trusteth in them.</hi> What ſtrange expectations have they from the ſuppoſed Vertue of their multiplyed <hi>Reliques,</hi> as if every little <hi>fragment</hi> that once belong'd
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41492:11"/>to a <hi>Saint,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King 13.21.</note> would (like the <hi>dead bones of Eliſha</hi>) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive others with a Touch! Tho, if we were to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend with them about theſe, (as the <hi>Archangel</hi> did with the <hi>Devil</hi> about the <hi>Body of Moſes</hi>) we ſhould find that the <hi>far greater part</hi> of them muſt needs be <hi>Counterfeits.</hi> What Mighty things will they fancy to be done by the preſence of the <hi>Host,</hi> which they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry often in <hi>Proceſſion,</hi> as if they did intend to match the <hi>Idolatrous Iſraelites</hi> exactly,<note place="margin">Exod. 32.1.</note> by <hi>having Gods which ſhould go before them!</hi> How unworthy are all theſe things to be compared with <hi>our Rock,</hi> with God (I mean) whoſe <hi>ſimilitude none ever ſaw,</hi> or with Chriſt, the <hi>expreſs</hi> and ſubſtantial <hi>Image of his</hi> Fathers <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon!</hi> How unfit are they to be <hi>laid in the ballance</hi> with a <hi>Living God,</hi> and a <hi>Glorified Redeemer!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, <hi>Indulgences</hi> and <hi>Pardons</hi> are another of <hi>their Rocks.</hi> Indeed, theſe are ſome of the chief <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements</hi> of the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> wherein (like <hi>Samſon's hair</hi>) they think that their <hi>great ſtrength lyes.</hi> For af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they have debaucht themſelves never ſo much, and <hi>ſtain'd</hi> their hands never ſo deeply (perhaps) in <hi>blood,</hi> they fancy that they may (with <hi>Pilate</hi>) <hi>waſh</hi> them by this means, and appear <hi>fair</hi> and unſpotted in God's ſight; As if there could be <hi>no condemnation</hi> to thoſe that have received the <hi>Prieſts Abſolution,</hi> or as if they might confidently <hi>alter</hi> thoſe triumphant words of the <hi>Apostle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.33.</note> and ſay, <hi>Who ſhall lay any thing to our charge? It is</hi> the Vicar of <hi>Chriſt that juſtifies us.</hi> Who knows not, that they truſt to <hi>the Key of David</hi> hanging at the Pope's Girdle, which ſhall <hi>open Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> to them, and <hi>ſhut Hell</hi> againſt them, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the Wickedneſs of their foregoing Lives? This is the <hi>Rock,</hi> which all the profligate Members of that Communion <hi>ſwim</hi> to, and which they are fatally <hi>Shipwrackt by;</hi> multitudes <hi>purchaſe a ſtanding</hi> upon
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41492:11"/>this dangerous and deceitful <hi>bottom,</hi> not only with the ſacrifice of their <hi>Eſtates,</hi> but the loſs of their <hi>Souls</hi> too. We <hi>Proteſtants</hi> on the contrary, though we are far from imagining that <hi>we have no ſin,</hi> yet we place all our hopes in <hi>Divine Forgiveneſs;</hi> believing that 'tis to no purpoſe for <hi>Men</hi> to <hi>remit our ſins,</hi> ſo long as <hi>God retains them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 55.1.</note> Our <hi>free</hi> pardon <hi>without Mony and without Price,</hi> is more <hi>effectual</hi> than that which they <hi>buy ſo dear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">v, </seg>2</label> Fifthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The <hi>Interceſſions</hi> of <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Saints</hi> are another <hi>Rock</hi> which <hi>they build</hi> much upon. They perſwade themſelves, that theſe <hi>Heavenly Courtiers</hi> have their <hi>King's Ear</hi> in every caſe, and that they are as <hi>attentive</hi> in <hi>liſtning</hi> to us, as <hi>ſucceſsful</hi> in <hi>pleading</hi> with God; more eſpecially, the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> (their <hi>Queen of Heaven</hi>) inveſted by them with greater Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority than all the reſt, ſo that ſhe need not to uſe the humble Style of <hi>intreating,</hi> but may take upon her to <hi>command her Son.</hi> But ſurely, if we could ſuppoſe that the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin</hi> in that perfect and ſinleſs ſtate above, could be guilty of ſuch <hi>preſumption,</hi> Our <hi>Exalted</hi> Saviour might with more reaſon ſay to her there,<note place="margin">John 2.4.</note> as he did at the <hi>Marriage in Cana</hi> (when ſhe only <hi>intimated</hi> to him, that <hi>they had no Wine,</hi> without ſo much as making any <hi>explicit requeſt</hi> for him to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide it) <hi>Woman, what have I to do with thee?</hi> Is not ſhe, and all the other <hi>Agents</hi> employ'd by <hi>that Church,</hi> perfectly diſcarded by <hi>that Text,</hi> which mentioning the relief that we have, <hi>if any man ſin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 John 2.1.</note> tells us only of <hi>an Advocate</hi> (which ſhews, that there is but <hi>one</hi>) <hi>with the Father, Jeſus Chriſt the Righteous?</hi> Such an <hi>Advocate for our Perſons,</hi> as that he is alſo the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation for our ſins,</hi> which they that <hi>are of Cephas</hi> (I mean, the <hi>Roman Faction</hi>) cannot ſay concerning <hi>him,</hi> or any Creature whatſoever. Now, who can
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41492:12"/>be ſo fit to <hi>intercede for us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.34.</note> as he that <hi>dyed for us?</hi> Who ſo worthy to <hi>plead our Cauſe,</hi> as he that <hi>paid our Debt?</hi> Who beſt deſerves to be <hi>always ſpoken to</hi> by us,<note place="margin">John 11.42.</note> but he, whom we know that God <hi>always hears?</hi> Who ſo likely to prevail in <hi>mediating</hi> with God, as he that from Eternity <hi>rejoyc't before him?</hi> What com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon is there between Jeſus Chriſt, and the <hi>higheſt</hi> Angels, or the <hi>beſt</hi> of Saints? Between an <hi>Omniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient High Prieſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.5.</note> and thoſe that <hi>know not any thing</hi> of our Affairs below?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixthly, The <hi>Merit of good Works</hi> is a principal <hi>Rock</hi> which our Enemies have <hi>choſen to themſelves.</hi> This (like the <hi>rich Mans Wealth</hi>) is <hi>their ſtrong Tower, and the high Wall to their own conceit.</hi> They look upon God as their <hi>Debtor,</hi> and go to him (as he in the <hi>parable</hi> did to his <hi>fellow Servant</hi>) crying,<note place="margin">Matth. 18.28.</note> 
               <hi>Pay me what thou oweſt;</hi> ſcorning to <hi>receive</hi> that as a <hi>Gift,</hi> which they think they may <hi>demand</hi> as <hi>Wages.</hi> I need not inſiſt here, (tho' 'tis moſt undeniably true) that the <hi>Works</hi> which they are ſo confident of <hi>meriting</hi> by, are not really <hi>good,</hi> becauſe a ſound and lively <hi>Faith</hi> is not the <hi>root</hi> of them; I ſay, I need not make uſe of this Argument againſt them here, for tho' we do <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve with our hearts,</hi> and perform all <hi>Acts of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> from that <hi>principle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.8.</note> yet we are <hi>ſaved by Grace,</hi> and that's the ſureſt <hi>foundation</hi> to raiſe our hopes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Mercy</hi> will be found the beſt and ſtrongeſt plea <hi>in the day of Judgment;</hi> and thoſe wretched <hi>drowning</hi> Sinners, that <hi>catch hold</hi> of any other <hi>twigs,</hi> ſhall ſink and periſh Everlaſtingly. Who can ſay, that his <hi>own Righteouſneſs</hi> is equal with the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> which the true <hi>Proteſtant</hi> deſires (like <hi>Paul</hi>) to be <hi>found in?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Philip. 3.9.</note> Who can compare his own <hi>filthy Rags</hi> (which are no better than <hi>Tinder,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel. 7.14.</note> if the <hi>Fire</hi> of God's Wrath ſhould <hi>fall upon</hi> them) to <hi>Robes waſhed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41492:12"/>white in the Blood of the Lamb?</hi> And therefore, as <hi>Balaam,</hi> after he had ſpent a great deal of time and pains, with hopes of <hi>curſing Iſrael,</hi> was conſtrain'd at laſt to <hi>bleſs</hi> them; ſo <hi>Bellarmine</hi> (a great <hi>Cardinal,</hi> and celebrated <hi>Author</hi> in the <hi>Church of Rome</hi>) when he had uſed abundance of ſubtilty in <hi>defending</hi> the Doctrine of <hi>Merit,</hi> he does in a manner, <hi>revoke</hi> all, by concluding, [<q rend="inline">Propter incertitudinem propriae Juſtitiae, &amp; periculum Inanis gloriae, tutiſſimum eſt fiduciam totam in ſolâ Dei miſericordiâ &amp; benig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate reponere.] <hi>Becauſe of the uncertainty of a perſonal Righteouſneſs, and the danger of vain glory, it is the ſecureſt courſe to put our whole truſt in the Mercy and goodneſs of God alone.</hi>
               </q> This leads me to</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> The <hi>Third</hi> thing, which is to ſhew, whence it comes to paſs, that <hi>even our Enemies judge</hi> our Rock to be better than our own. Briefly, there may be theſe three <hi>grounds</hi> and reaſons of it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, There is a <hi>mighty Evidence</hi> in ſome <hi>Truths,</hi> which <hi>cannot be reſiſted</hi> by Men of the moſt <hi>corrupt minds.</hi> The <hi>Light</hi> of Nature is not ſo far <hi>put out</hi> in the vileſt Perſons, but that they do <hi>ſee</hi> ſome of the Differences between <hi>good and evil.</hi> Indeed the <hi>deep Myſteries</hi> of the Goſpel are ſuch as <hi>cannot be known by Natural Men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.14.</note> but there are other Truths ſo manifeſt and notorious, that they <hi>cannot</hi> eaſily <hi>be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant</hi> of them; 'tis almoſt impoſſible to <hi>hide</hi> them from their <hi>underſtandings,</hi> and Conviction <hi>breaks in</hi> againſt their Wills. It may be in their power to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> many things, which 'tis not in their power to <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believe;</hi> their Tongues perhaps may ſpeak in <hi>oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to that, which their Judgments do <hi>neceſſarily aſſent</hi> to; as the Devil may be the Author of <hi>Atheiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41492:13"/>Suggestions</hi> to others, tho' he cannot doubt of the being of God <hi>himſelf.</hi> I queſtion not, but that our Enemies <hi>would</hi> judge <hi>their Rock</hi> to be better than <hi>ours,</hi> if they could bring their <hi>thoughts,</hi> as well as their <hi>Words,</hi> ſo much <hi>under their own Command;</hi> therefore we muſt conclude, that they think <hi>thus,</hi> becauſe they are not able to avoid it by thinking <hi>otherwiſe</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, <hi>Signal Rebukes</hi> of <hi>Providence</hi> do many times make this Truth more plain to our Enemies, of the <hi>Incomparable Excellency</hi> of our Rock. Then it becomes as <hi>legible</hi> to them, as the <hi>Handwriting</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Wall to <hi>Belſhazzar;</hi> and they diſcern it as clearly,<note place="margin">Exod. 8.19.</note> as <hi>Pharaohs Magicians</hi> did <hi>the finger of God,</hi> when they could no longer imitate the <hi>miraculous Works of Moſes</hi> by their <hi>Enchantments.</hi> If <hi>Dagon</hi> cannot ſtand before the <hi>Ark of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 5.2.</note> even in the <hi>houſe of Dagon,</hi> but like a poor helpleſs God be dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of from his <hi>own dunghil,</hi> it muſt needs in ſome meaſure <hi>open the eyes</hi> of thoſe that are moſt <hi>in love with darkneſs.</hi> When God <hi>fruſtrates</hi> the moſt probable <hi>tokens of the Lyers,</hi> and <hi>turns</hi> the wiſeſt <hi>counſells into fooliſhneſs:</hi> When he <hi>brings his wheel</hi> on a ſudden over their necks, that are trampling upon others, and makes Men's own <hi>contrivances</hi> and <hi>preparations</hi> moſt perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and fatal to themſelves: When Enemyes that were wont to be attended with the ſtrangeſt <hi>ſucceſſes,</hi> fall afterwards under as ſurprizing <hi>diſappointments,</hi> and the <hi>ſtream of proſperity</hi> which hath <hi>carried all</hi> before them, <hi>runs</hi> as ſtrong againſt them: This will certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make them <hi>reflect</hi> (though Satan bend all his cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to <hi>ſtiſte</hi> ſuch Reflexions) upon the <hi>weakneſs</hi> of the Rock which they truſt in. There are ſome <hi>appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances</hi> of God in all his works: he does nothing, but what <hi>declares the glory</hi> of the Agent: nevertheleſs
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41492:13"/>there are <hi>particular diſpenſations</hi> alſo towards the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Church,<note place="margin">Pſal. 9.16.</note> wherein <hi>the Lord is</hi> eminently <hi>known by the Judgments which he executeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, The <hi>Terrours of God</hi> are a Demonſtration of this truth ſometimes to Adverſaries, even <hi>in the midſt of their proſperity.</hi> I do not think that <hi>Babylon,</hi> even while ſhe <hi>ſits as a Queen,</hi> can fortifie her <hi>Children</hi> againſt inward <hi>Convulſions,</hi> or that they who ſeem above the fears of any <hi>viſible diſturbance,</hi> are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alwayes <hi>perfectly at eaſe;</hi> the <hi>Worm</hi> of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence may be <hi>biting,</hi> while their <hi>Gourd</hi> is <hi>flouriſhing;</hi> the <hi>Spirits</hi> of <hi>Iſraels troublers</hi> may be <hi>troubled,</hi> and when their <hi>voice</hi> to others is <hi>as the roaring of a Lyon.</hi> God may <hi>ſpeak</hi> more dreadfully <hi>in his Wrath</hi> to them.<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.5.</note> He who can <hi>touch the Mountains,</hi> ſo as to make them <hi>ſmoak,</hi> can make the <hi>Pillars</hi> of the Antichriſtian Kingdom <hi>tremble,</hi> and their Hearts <hi>aſtoniſhed at his reproof.</hi> This way of God's dealing with the <hi>minds</hi> of Men, is worſe than the heavieſt ſtrokes of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence falling upon their <hi>outward concerns;</hi> 'tis many times indeed induſtriouſly <hi>cover'd</hi> and diſſembled by thoſe that <hi>feel</hi> it (who know how to <hi>laugh,</hi> when they have more cauſe to <hi>howl</hi>) but it cannot be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally <hi>eſcap't,</hi> nor quietly <hi>endur'd.</hi> It will <hi>unſettle</hi> Men <hi>from their lees,</hi> and beget a <hi>ſenſe</hi> of God's excellent greatneſs, and (it may be) will extort ſuch an <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment</hi> alſo, as it did from lofty <hi>Nebuchadne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi> at the beginning of his <hi>Reign,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 2.47.</note> that <hi>our God is the God of Gods.</hi> If God do <hi>work</hi> upon the Souls of Enemies, as he is able to do, (without <hi>letting looſe his</hi> viſible <hi>hand</hi> againſt them) he can bring <hi>every knee</hi> to <hi>bow,</hi> and <hi>every tongue</hi> to <hi>confeſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:41492:14"/>
            <p>If any ſhould now ask,<note place="margin">Q.</note> Why <hi>Our Enemies</hi> cleave to <hi>their Rock</hi> ſtill, ſeeing they muſt be <hi>ſecretly convinc't,</hi> that <hi>our Rock</hi> is better, the Anſwer is eaſie.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">A. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Common Convictions</hi> (ſuch as <hi>they</hi> at any time lye under) are very weak and <hi>ineffectual,</hi> as to the altering of Mens <hi>ſtate</hi> and <hi>cuſtomary practice.</hi> The meer ſpeculative <hi>knowledge</hi> of Divine Truths hath but ſmall influence in producing a Reformation, when they are not <hi>deeply imprinted</hi> by the Spirit of God, and backt with an Holy <hi>experience. No man</hi> (ſays our Saviour) <hi>having drunk old Wine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 5.39.</note> 
               <hi>deſireth new;</hi> but the <hi>new</hi> may ſtill ſatisfie thoſe that never had any more than a <hi>Notion</hi> of the goodneſs of the <hi>Old.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.2.3.</note> Thoſe Spiritual <hi>taſts</hi> and reliſhes which Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers have, incline them to a <hi>love of the Word,</hi> and keep them from following after <hi>Fables.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, The <hi>Pride</hi> of their Hearts will not ſuffer them to <hi>deſtroy,</hi> what they have been <hi>building up</hi> for ſo many hundreds of Years. They muſt <hi>pull down the whole frame</hi> of their Church, if they entertain any thoughts of a <hi>new foundation.</hi> They muſt <hi>abandon</hi> all that they have been fiercely <hi>contending</hi> for ſo long, if they eſpouſe <hi>our Rock,</hi> and quit <hi>their own.</hi> It will not be enough to give up a few <hi>leſs material points,</hi> but their <hi>main principles</hi> muſt be renounc't alſo. And this is too <hi>hard a ſaying</hi> for thoſe who have <hi>puff't up</hi> themſelves with a vain Opinion, that they <hi>cannot err.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, The powerful Temptation of <hi>Worldly Intereſt</hi> will hinder <hi>ſuch a change.</hi> For, they muſt then ſtrip themſelves of all that <hi>pomp</hi> and <hi>grandeur,</hi> and lay aſide all thoſe cunning Artifices of <hi>robbing</hi> the People to increaſe their <hi>Churches Treaſure,</hi> which recommends that Religion ſo much to the <hi>Luſts of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41492:14"/>Men.</hi> They know not how to ſacrifice the <hi>pleaſure</hi> of <hi>Domination,</hi> or to leave that <hi>profitable Trade</hi> of the <hi>Merchandiſe of Souls,</hi> which they muſt do, if they make choice of <hi>our God,</hi> and be reconcil'd to <hi>our Religion. Great Poſſeſſions</hi> and <hi>Honours</hi> do very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, even in leſſer caſes, prejudice Men againſt the Doctrine of the <hi>Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, Their <hi>Conſciences</hi> are Judicially <hi>ſeared;</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtle Paul</hi> foretold of theſe <hi>Grand Apoſtates in the latter times.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.2. 2 Theſs. 2.11.</note> They are under <hi>ſtrong deluſions</hi> (as the ſame Perſon ſpeaks of them elſewhere) by the <hi>Righteous Judgment</hi> of God, who, becauſe they have left the <hi>truth,</hi> hath left them to themſelves. Perhaps God may have a <hi>Remnant of People,</hi> that are yet <hi>in Babylon,</hi> whom he will <hi>call out</hi> from thence before the time of her <hi>final deſtruction;</hi> but as to the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, and <hi>main body</hi> of that Church (and more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, the <hi>Learned Men</hi> in it) they ſeem to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd over to a <hi>reprobate mind;</hi> and the <hi>hardneſs of their hearts</hi> is become both their <hi>ſin</hi> and their <hi>puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> too. So hopeleſs an Attempt is <hi>that</hi> of <hi>Healing</hi> thoſe whom God hath determined to <hi>cut off.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> In the <hi>laſt place,</hi> I am to <hi>Apply</hi> all this, with <hi>ſome relation to the Day.</hi> Several things may be Inferr'd from the foregoing Diſcourſe, which are very <hi>proper</hi> to be conſider'd by us <hi>now.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Firſt, If our <hi>Enemies themſelves</hi> cannot but <hi>judge,</hi> that <hi>their Rock is not as our Rock,</hi> then we have a <hi>Witneſs for us</hi> in their own boſoms, that our <hi>Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> from them was <hi>just</hi> and <hi>neceſſary.</hi> They cannot blame or cenſure the <hi>Reformed Churches</hi> that have forſaken their Communion, without ſome inward <hi>check</hi> upon their Spirits. When they call us <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:41492:15"/>and give us all the other opprobrious Names they can invent, 'tis ſcarcely poſſible that they ſhould forbear to think, (as <hi>Saul</hi> ſaid to <hi>David</hi>) that <hi>we are more righteous than they;</hi> and therefore their <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting</hi> and <hi>blaſpheming</hi> (like thoſe <hi>malicious Jews</hi>) is the <hi>greater ſin.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 13.45.</note> As <hi>Pilate,</hi> even when he <hi>condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> Chriſt, did declare him innocent and <hi>faultleſs,</hi> ſo while our <hi>Adverſaries</hi> revile us, and thunder out their <hi>Excommunications</hi> againſt us, there is ſtill <hi>ſomething within</hi> them, which <hi>gives ſentence</hi> for us. How little then is the <hi>evil</hi> which they <hi>ſpeak,</hi> to be regarded, when their <hi>own Hearts</hi> tell them, that they <hi>lye</hi> in ſpeaking it!</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, This teaches us, that we may very well <hi>pray in Faith</hi> for their <hi>Confuſion:</hi> (The <hi>Scripture</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging us to expect this, much more than their <hi>Converſion.</hi>) Their <hi>Rock</hi> is but a <hi>Quick-ſand</hi> which will <hi>ſwallow</hi> them up, or as a <hi>Milstone</hi> to <hi>drown</hi> them, Inſtead of a <hi>foundation</hi> to <hi>bear</hi> them. What therefore ſhould make us afraid of uſing the <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mist's</hi> words,<note place="margin">Pſal. 97.7.</note> with the ſame <hi>hope</hi> that was in him of their accompliſhment! <hi>Confounded be all they that ſerve graven Images, that boast themſelves of Idols.</hi> What ſhould make us doubt, but that the <hi>doom</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc't by the <hi>Prophet</hi> will be executed on <hi>their Gods!</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jerem. 51.18.</note> 
               <hi>They are vanity, the work of Errours; in the time of their viſitation they ſhall periſh.</hi> During the <hi>time</hi> of God's forbearance, and of the <hi>patience of Jeſus Christ,</hi> we ſhould be praying, that this <hi>time of viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> may be haſten'd, as Men who are aſſur'd, that their <hi>fall ſhall be great,</hi> and that after it they ſhall <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver riſe more.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 11.2.</note> Let all that <hi>make Interceſſion against Babylon</hi> (as <hi>Elias</hi> did againſt <hi>Iſrael</hi>) believe this firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the <hi>Golden Cup</hi> which is now in her hand
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41492:15"/>
               <hi>full of abominable filthineſs,</hi> ſhall <hi>run over</hi> at laſt with <hi>Divine fury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, This ſhews how <hi>fooliſhly</hi> and <hi>unjuſtly</hi> the <hi>ſucceſſes</hi> of God's Enemyes are at any time attributed to <hi>their own Rock.</hi> This hath been their practice of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; as the <hi>Philiſtins offered a great Sacrifice to Dagon their God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. 16.23, 24.</note> when they had gotten <hi>Sampſon</hi> in their hands. So the <hi>Adherents of Antichriſt</hi> have <hi>praiſed their Gods of Gold and Silver, of Wood and Stone,</hi> and made their acknowledgment to their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>Imaginary Saints,</hi> when they have <hi>proſper'd</hi> in any of their Deſigns. But how much are they <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken</hi> and deluded in all this! How do they <hi>offend</hi> (like the <hi>Caldaeans</hi> of old) in <hi>imputing this power to their God,</hi> which they receive from <hi>ours!</hi>
               <note place="margin">Habac. 1.11.</note> We read of the <hi>Holy City</hi> being <hi>given to the</hi> (Popiſh),<note place="margin">Revel. 11.2.</note> 
               <hi>Gentiles to tread under foot</hi> for a limited time; now who can <hi>give</hi> it to them, beſides the <hi>Lord of all,</hi> who does it, when he pleaſes, in order to wiſe and <hi>holy ends?</hi> An <hi>Idol,</hi> which is <hi>nothing in the World,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Corinth. 8.4.</note> (<hi>i.e.</hi> hath no <hi>efficacy</hi> or vertue) is worthy only to <hi>inhabit the praiſes</hi> of ſuch <hi>as the horſe and mule, which have no un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, If out Rock be <hi>ſo much better</hi> than theirs, how carefully ſhould we <hi>walk before him,</hi> that he may <hi>continue to be Ours!</hi> That we may not be <hi>diſpoſſest</hi> of our Intereſt in him, nor <hi>broken off</hi> from our Relation to him. The ſame God who hath <hi>turned our Captivity</hi> from us, is able to <hi>bring it back</hi> again; and he that hath <hi>ſet our feet in a large place,</hi> can yet <hi>ſhut us up into the hands of our Enemies.</hi> 'Tis eaſie with God to <hi>undo</hi> all that he hath <hi>done,</hi> if we <hi>abuſe his Mercy</hi> by groundleſs preſumption, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful impenitency. The <hi>greatest Judgments</hi> do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41492:16"/>times come after the <hi>greatest deliverances.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jude 5.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord having ſaved the People out of the Land of Egypt, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward destroyed them that believed not.</hi> 'Tis very poſſible,<note place="margin">Joſh. 23.15.</note> that God <hi>may bring all evil things</hi> upon the ſame Perſons, upon whom <hi>all good things have come.</hi> Our <hi>Mountain</hi> does not <hi>ſtand ſo ſtrong,</hi> but that our ſins may breed an <hi>Earthquake</hi> to unſettle and <hi>remove</hi> it. No humane <hi>Policy</hi> or <hi>Power</hi> can protect us, if our God ſhould <hi>depart</hi> from us. We read, that <hi>the Army of the Syrians came with a ſmall Company of Men against the Iſraelites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chro. 24.24.</note> 
               <hi>and the Lord deliver'd a very great Host into their band, becauſe they had forſaken the Lord God of their Fathers.</hi> And if theſe <hi>Nations</hi> ſhould ſo loſe <hi>their God</hi> after ſuch amazing Inſtances of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence with them, how diſmal would their condition be! If God ſhould be provok't to <hi>turn away his wrath</hi> from our Adverſaries,<note place="margin">Prov. 24.18.</note> and pour it out <hi>afreſh</hi> upon us, <hi>to whom ſhould we flee for help?</hi> If our <hi>Rock ſhould ſell us,</hi> who of our <hi>Confederate Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours</hi> is able to <hi>Redeem us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, Let our Rock have <hi>the Glory due unto his Name</hi> for the TWO <hi>Great Salvations</hi> which <hi>This Day</hi> brings to our remembrance; I mean, That which was wrought for our Fore-fathers ſo <hi>many years</hi> ago, and That which was wrought for us but <hi>One year</hi> ſince. God hath honoured this Day with a <hi>Double Mercy,</hi> let us honour God by yielding to him a <hi>Double Sacrifice of Praiſe; binding it,</hi> as with a twiſted <hi>Cord to the Horns of the Altar.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 118.27.</note> Let us raiſe a <hi>Pillar</hi> of thankfulneſs with ſuch a laſting <hi>Inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> as neither <hi>Time,</hi> nor any <hi>other Hands</hi> may ever be able to <hi>deface.</hi> Both <hi>our Fore fathers</hi> and <hi>we</hi> were deliver'd from the <hi>ſame Enemies,</hi> tho' not ſtrictly from the very <hi>ſame methods of Conſpiracy;</hi> formerly they
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41492:16"/>aim'd at the deſtruction of the <hi>Lawgivers</hi> by <hi>one blow,</hi> but lately at the ſubverſion of the <hi>Laws</hi> themſelves by more <hi>gradual meaſures;</hi> in the <hi>Powder Treaſon</hi> they had contriv'd to <hi>blow up</hi> the <hi>Perſons</hi> of our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, and for ſome years paſt they have been <hi>laying the Train</hi> to <hi>blow up our Constitution.</hi> Bleſſed be that God, who ſo ſeaſonably prevented both the <hi>one,</hi> and the <hi>other. This Day</hi> might have been <hi>a Day of trouble and rebuke and blaſphemy.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings 19.3.</note> (as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> once complain'd); and ſo it would have been indeed, if when the <hi>Children were come to the birth,</hi> there had not been <hi>ſtrength to bring forth;</hi> I mean if God had <hi>frown'd upon</hi> the Glorious Undertaking of our <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Soveraign,</hi> which <hi>this day</hi> begun to take effect. <hi>Let not Darkneſs</hi> therefore, <hi>nor the Shadow</hi> of Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vion ever <hi>ſtain this day; let no cloud dwell upon it; let no mournful voice be heard therein.</hi> Who is there, that bears <hi>Good will to our Sion,</hi> that will not reckon it the beſt in our <hi>Engliſh Calendar,</hi> and moſt worthy, above all others, to be <hi>joyned to the Days of the Year?</hi> In ſhort, Let <hi>Our Mouths be filled with God's Praiſe, and with his Honour</hi> all this Day long, and let our <hi>Converſations practically</hi> expreſs it all our Life long; That our Holy Gratitude for the Mercies which we <hi>have,</hi> may fit us for thoſe which we <hi>want;</hi> that our <hi>Sun</hi> may neither <hi>go backward,</hi> nor <hi>stand still,</hi> but make haſt (in God's <hi>due time</hi>) to <hi>finiſh its remaining courſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:41492:17"/>
            <head>
               <hi>BOOKS Sold by</hi> John Salusbury, <hi>at the</hi> Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Sun, <hi>near the</hi> Royal Exchange <hi>in</hi> Cornhil.</head>
            <p>THE Mighty Wonders of a Merciful Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, in a Sermon Preached on the Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving-day, <hi>Jan.</hi> 31. 1689.</p>
            <p>The Duty and Support of Believers in Life and Death.</p>
            <p>The Period of Humane Life determined by the Divine Will.</p>
            <p>The Uſefulneſs of Spiritual Wiſdom, with a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Inheritance.</p>
            <p>The Churches Plea for the Divine Preſence to proſper Humane Force; in a Sermon preacht on the Faſt-day, <hi>Jan.</hi> 5. 1689. All 5 by the ſame Author.</p>
            <p>A Rational Defence of Nonconformity: Wherein the Practice of Nonconformiſts is vindicated from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting Popery, and Ruining the Church, imputed to them by Dr. <hi>Stilling fleet</hi> in his Unreaſonableneſs of Separation. Alſo his Arguments from the Principles and Way of the Reformers. and firſt Diſſenters are Anſwered. And the Caſe of the preſent Separation truly ſtated; and the blame of it laid where it ought to be. And the way to Union among Proteſtants is pointed at, by <hi>Gilbert Rule,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>The Conformiſts Charity to Diſſenters, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence with the Favour granted them in the Act for Toleration, proved from the Works of the moſt Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Divines of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Certain Sermons or Homilies appointed to be read in Churches in the time of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> in Two Parts, in Twelves, price 3 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chirurgorum Comes, or the whole Practice of Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgery, begun by the Learned Dr. <hi>Read,</hi> Continued and Compleated by a Member of the College of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
